Guide to the Kathleen Hanna Papers MSS.271
Fales Library and Special Collections
Kathleen Hanna Papers
1988-2015
Fales Library and Special Collections
Hanna, Kathleen, 1968-
MSS.271
7 Linear Feet in 10 document cases, 1 flat box, 2 binders, 1 oversize box, 1 flat file folder, and 3 folders in shared housing
2.38 Gigabytes in 2 computer files
Kathleen Hanna was an early instigator of the Riot Grrrl Movement, performing in bands such as Bikini Kill and Le Tigre. The Kathleen Hanna Papers consists of flyers, posters, zines and zine masters, notebooks, ephemera, magazines, photographs, media, newspaper clippings, theses and other academic writing, and legal and financial records. The collection documents Hanna's artistic production, participation in the Riot Grrrl movement, curatorial work, and musical career.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to NYU Libraries in 2010. An accretion to the collection was received in 2015; the accession number associated with this gift is 2016.045. A further accretion was received in August 2022; the accession number associated with this gift is 2023.018.
Arrangement
Series List:
Series I: Filing Cabinet
Series II: Photo Binders
Series III: Media
Series IV: Computer Disks
Series V. 2015 Accretion
OVERSIZE SERIES I
All efforts were made to preserve the original arrangement of the collection, with the exception of oversize materials and zine flats which are housed separately.
Biographical Note
Kathleen Hanna was an early instigator of the Riot Grrrl movement in the early 1990's in both Olympia, Washington and Washington, DC. Along with Allison Wolfe she organized the first Riot Grrrl meeting, collaborated on several early Riot Grrrl zines, and was a major force behind the first Riot Grrrl Convention.
From 1990-1997 she was a member of the most widely recognized "Riot Grrrl Band", Bikini Kill. She co-authored the band's zines, including their 1992 Bikini Kill #2 which used the phrase "Girl Power" for the first time. Bikini Kill toured the states extensively and also played shows in Europe, Japan and Australia.
Her second large scale feminist DIY project was the electronic band Le Tigre which was active from 1999-2006. This band used activism as a jumping-off point for their visually stimulating live shows and their three full-length albums. Le Tigre played everywhere, from Massachussetts to St. Petersburg.
Hanna currently lives in NYC and is active as a musician and lecturer.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Related Materials
Johanna Fateman Riot Grrrl Papers (MSS 258)
Molly Neuman Riot Grrrl Collection (MSS 289)
Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection (MSS 290)
Tammy Rae Carland Zine Collection (MSS 320)
Riot Grrrl Publicity Collection (MSS 316)
Mr. Lady Archive (unprocessed) (MSS 362)
Scope and Contents
The Kathleen Hanna Papers consist of materials created and collected by Hanna documenting her artistic production and participation in the Riot Grrrl movement, as well as her broader musical career and curatorial endeavors. Materials include flyers, posters, zines and zine masters, notebooks, ephemera, magazines, photographs, audio and video recordings of live performances and studio recordings, newspaper and magazine clippings, theses and other academic writings, and legal and financial records.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Born-digital materials in Series IV: Computer Disks have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Musicians -- 1990-2000; Posters.; Interactive art.; Lesbians -- United States; Zines; Dance music -- United States; Art -- Exhibitions.; Punk rock music.; Women artists -- United States.; Riot grrrl movement.; Feminist punk electronic music.; Washington (D.C.); Correspondence.; Contracts; Contact sheets.; Compact discs.; Color slides.; Color photographs.; Address books; Administrative records; Agreements.; Albums.; Alternative spaces (Arts facilities).; Art -- Exhibitions -- New York (N.Y.); Art |x Experimental methods.; Articles.; Artists and community -- United States; Color negatives.; Tax records.; Student projects.; Videocassettes.; Video recordings.; Works of art.; Women's rights.; Multimedia (Art).; Olympia (Wash.); Punk culture.; Fanzines.; Electronic music.; Feminism; Feminism and art.; Press kits.; Politics in art.; Magazines (Periodicals); Feminist music; Memorabilia.; Negatives (photographic); New York (N.Y.).; Personal correspondence.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Poetry.; Printed ephemera.; Essays.; Exhibition catalogs.; Fliers (printed matter); Gender identity -- United States; Juvenilia.; Lyric sheets.; Carland, Tammy Rae, 1965-; Fateman, Johanna, 1974-; Bikini Kill (Musical group); Ruin, Julie, 1968-; Le Tigre (Musical group); Evergreen State College
- Series I: Filing Cabinet Files
  Scope and Content
  This series is comprised of the contents of a filing cabinet in which Hanna stored Riot Grrrl related materials from the early 1990s until the collection was donated to Fales in 2010. The series contains flyers, posters, zines, notebooks and other materials related to the Riot Grrrl Movement; ephemera, press clippings, and legal and financial records of musical projects including Viva Knievel, Bikini Kill, Le Tigre and Julie Ruin; writing for spoken word performances and zines; materials that Hanna collected including articles with an emphasis on feminst theory, artwork by friends such as Tammy Rae Carland, and theses and other writing inspired by the Riot Grrrl movment and Hanna's work; photographs and other materials related to curatorial work at the Evergreen State College, Reko Muse and the Spring Street Gallery; personal materials including student records from Evergreen State College, personal legal and financial records, and a limited amount of correspondence from Johanna Fateman.
  - Dear Daddy Master [zine] [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dear Daddy Master [zine] [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fuck Me Blind [zine] [1 of 3], 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fuck Me Blind [zine] [2 of 3], 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fuck Me Blind [zine] [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Most Beautiful Girl is a Dead Girl [zine] [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Abstract
    Hanna's alter ego Maggie Fingers' collection of loosely centralized narrative fiction covers a variety of themes, such as masculinity in the context of oppression of women by partners and fathers, objectification, and sexual abuse. Fingers also addresses the ubiquity of the white male perspective, oppression and stereotyping of racial minorities, the tensions and superficiality endemic to family life, and the power and entrapment of beauty are explored. Writings on sexual fantasy and relationships counter musings on isolation and abandonment. A theme of medical sickness applies in text and imagery throughout, and the narrative point of view changes.
  - The Most Beautiful Girl is a Dead Girl [zine] [2 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Most Beautiful Girl is a Dead Girl [zine master] [1 of 3], undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Most Beautiful Girl is a Dead Girl [zine master] [2 of 3], undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Most Beautiful Girl is a Dead Girl [3 of 3], undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - College [1 of 2], 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - College [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bikini Kill Zine #1 [1 of 2], [1990] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This zine, put out by the members of the riot grrrl band Bikini Kill, features illustrations, lists, photographs, advertisements, song lyrics, short essays, information on female musicians, and an extended interview with another the band Mecca Normal. White privilege, the importance of female musicians, female empowerment, and resisting jealousy are important themes.
  - Bikini Kill Zine #1 [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [1990] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bikini Kill Zine #1 [zine master], [1990] (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Bikini Kill Zine #2 [1 of 2], [1991] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    The second issue of riot grrrl band Bikini Kill's zine provides updates on the band's touring and publishing exploits and reacts to their mainstream media coverage. The social movement is also considered in broader terms, with discussions on complacency and dogma that diminish radical activism, origins of the movement, and calls for participation. Manifesto writings by Kathleen Hanna are included. Other themes include the questioning of acting and being perceived as cool and the refusal to explain feminist motives and actions to men. Also contains a letters from male and female fans about feminism, an excerpt on fat oppression and liberation, an interview with dyke band Tribe 8 on punk and challenging conceptions of lesbianism, a piece on sex worker self-advocacy, and and extended list of debunked male criticisms of feminism. Local scene news is also discussed.
  - Bikini Kill Zine #2 [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [1991] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bikini Kill Zine #2 [zine master] [1 of 2], [1991] (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bikini Kill Zine #2 [zine master] [2 of 2], [1991] (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Ideas [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ideas [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Friends' Work [1 of 5], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Friends' Work [2 of 5], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Friends' Work [3 of 5], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Friends' Work [4 of 5], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Friends' Work [5 of 5] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Tammy Rae Carland [1 of 4], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Tammy Rae Carland [2 of 4], undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Tammy Rae Carland [3 of 4], undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Tammy Rae Carland [4 of 4] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tammy Rae Carland [large photo], undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - [Writings] [1 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - [Writings] [2 of 2], undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Spoken Word [1 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Spoken Word [2 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Spoken Word [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bikini Kill Logos [1 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bikini Kill Logos [2 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bikini Kill Logos [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folders], undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bikini Kill Masters- Fliers, Record covers, Stickers [1 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bikini Kill Masters- Fliers, Record Covers, Stickers [2 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bikini Kill Masters- Fliers, Record Covers, Stickers [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Other Masters [1 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Other Masters [2 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Other Masters [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Things I Made [1 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Things I Made [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - [Bikini Kill] Tour [1 of 2], 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - [Bikini Kill] Tour [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - My Life With Evan Dando Popstar [zine] [1 of 2], [1994] (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Xeroxed in red, blue, and black, Hanna's critical fanzine centers on Evan Dando as a complex symbol of male desirability and oppression. Her obsession with the public figure is documented as both a distraction from and an abstract reflection on her continuing areas of thought. She discusses his background of privilege, ability to successfully exploit his sexuality for fame, and considers the vapidity of his personality on the basis of his public persona. This is contrasted with discussions on the demonization of sex workers, and musings on the antisocial serial killer of feminists, Mark Lepine. Hanna reiterates her frustration with the tension between her feelings of desire and repulsion toward Dando.
  - My Life With Evan Dando Popstar [zine] [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [1994] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - My Life With Evan Dando Popstar [zine master], [1994] (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Resume [1 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Resume [2 of 3], undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Resume [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notebook- "Riot Grrrl Test Patterns", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - [Riot Grrrl Zines/Flyers] [1 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Riot Grrrl [NYC] [no. 5]
    Quotes from various girls about what riot grrrl means are dispersed throughout this zine. Media critiques include examples of the backlash against the movement in the press, as well as critiques of the mainstream girls' magazine Sassy. Calls for participation include sexual abuse and radical activism projects. Personal writings cover relationships with mothers abundantly, in addition to the destructive effects of drug use to friendship. The zine features reviews of books and local art concerning women and women's issues. An audio compilation of spoken word to support pro-choice movement is described. The zine concludes with an extended interview with Jennifer Blowdryer and an excerpt from her book Wrong Wrong Wrong.
    Riot Grrrl: A Free Weekly Mini-Zine [DC] [no. 4]
    Issue four of this Washington, D.C.-based mini-zine focuses primarily on personal writings. Beginning with a piece describing the feeling inspired by live female performance in music, the zine continues with a musing about the freeform nature of riot grrrl: the lack of codification, leadership, or a specific agenda or set of goals. Later entries include a memoir concerning domestic violence in the family, sketches, and a "fashion doctrine corollary" that considers personal appearance in light of social and personal struggle. Following are first-person writings on empathy, the desire to share strength with women who have been sexually objectified by men, critiques of religion in the context of domestic violence, and the insecurity of adolescence. Personal top ten lists also appear throughout.
    Riot Grrrl: A Free Weekly Mini-Zine - 7.10.91
    Members of Bratmobile and Bikini Kill from Olympia, WA published the first issue of mini-zine during their time in Washington, D.C. Intended as a weekly, this issue contains an introduction, ideas for subversive riots and scams, and extensive local news relating to new zines, live and recorded music, events, and other miscellany. The upcoming International Pop Underground festival is emphasized. Following entries contain personal writings covering female empowerment (Kathleen Hanna's "Burn Down the Walls that Say You Can't"), the oppression of heteronormativity, ironic erotic fiction, the D.C. Metro, and sexist, violent attitudes toward women. Concludes with a call for submissions.
    Riot Grrrl Press: Spring and Summer Catalog 1998
    Issued when the distribution service relocated to Portland, this catalog contains an alphabetical listing of zines spanning several years and numerous topics including music, travel, sex, politics, and personal issues. Author-submitted descriptions are included, as are names in some cases. Available films and compilations are listed, in addition to other distros. The origins of the press are also discussed, as is its mandate to distribute anything sent in.
    Riot Grrrl Press Catalogue: Early 1994
    This copy of the distribution service catalog was actually mailed in 1995. Contains news and information about the press and its operations funding. Discusses six main reasons why the press is important. Zines, spanning several years and numerous topics including music, travel, sex, politics, and personal issues, are listed alphabetically. Author-submitted descriptions are included, as are names in some cases. Information and addresses for non-distro zines as well as several riot grrrl chapters are also included.
  - [Riot Grrrl Zines/Flyers] [2 of 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    This issue of the distribution service catalog was actually mailed in 1995. Contains news and information about the press and its operations funding. Discusses six main reasons why the press is important. Zines, spanning several years and numerous topics including music, travel, sex, politics, and personal issues, are listed alphabetically. Author-submitted descriptions are included, as are names in some cases. Information and addresses for non-distro zines as well as several riot grrrl chapters are also included.
    Riot Grrrl Review! no. 3 Winter 1996 / Spring 1997
    This review zine, based in Ft. Myers, FL, contains a listings and reviews of zines, distros, and relevant resources with associated address information for ordering. Author Kristy also responds to feedback from the previous issue, briefly muses on riot grrrl, explains her reviewing policy, and provides her top ten list of zines from the issue.
  - 23 Wishes [Kathleen Hanna Newsletter zine] [1 of 2], [1996] (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Hanna's personal newsletter zine, published with two different covers, serves as a blanket response to questions commonly asked in her deluge of fan mail. Early in the zine, she describes her role as a resource for women seeking counsel about domestic violence and sexual abuse, as well as her inability to maintain this effort for the large number of victims seeking support. She offers advice and points toward alternative media and resources centered on these issues. Numerous updates on Bikini Kill are provided, as well as personal recommendations, reviews, and contact information for zines and music. She also answers basic questions about riot grrrl and describes her dissociation from the movement. The backstory and jailing of Mumia Abu-Jamal is covered in detail, and Hanna calls for support and publicity of a movement for his cause.
  - 23 Wishes [Kathleen Hanna Newsletter zine] [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [1996] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - [Kathleen Hanna Newsletter zine master] [1 of 3], [1996] (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - [Kathleen Hanna Newsletter zine master] [2 of 3], [1996] (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - [Kathleen Hanna Newsletter zine master] [3 of 3], [1996] (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - April Fools Day no. 1 [zine] [1 of 2], [1995] (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Kathleen Hanna, lead singer of Riot Grrrl band Bikini Kill, writes about her struggle with alcoholism and its effect on her life in this personal zine. Also included are non-destructive ways to get high, things that are better when sober, and a conversation about addiction with Brian Starhawk of Fitz of Depression.
  - April Fools Day no. 1 [zine] [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [1995] (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - April Fools Day no. 1 [zine master] [1 of 3], [1995] (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - April Fools Day no. 1 [zine master] [2 of 3], [1995] (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - April Fools Day no. 1 [zine master] [3 of 3], [1995] (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - articles [1 of 11], undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - articles [2 of 11], undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - articles [3 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - articles [4 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - articles [5 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - articles [6 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - articles [7 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - articles [8 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - articles [9 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - articles [10 of 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - articles [11 of 11] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Courtney [Love] Thing [1 of 3], [1994-1996] (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Courtney [Love] Thing [2 of 3], [1994-1996] (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Courtney [Love] Thing [3 of 3] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [1994-1996] (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Gallery stuff [1 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gallery stuff [2 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gallery stuff [3 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gallery stuff [4 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gallery stuff [5 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Gallery stuff [6 of 6] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Writings about Bikini Kill, Riot Grrrl,"The Scene" [1 of 5], undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Writings about Bikini Kill, Riot Grrrl,"The Scene" [2 of 5], undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Writings About Bikini Kill, Riot Grrrl, "The Scene" [3 of 5], undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Writings About Bikini Kill, Riot Grrrl, "The Scene" [4 of 5], undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Writings About Bikini Kill, Riot Grrrl, "The Scene" [5 of 5] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Old Lyrics [1 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Old Lyrics [2 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Old Lyrics [3 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Old Lyrics [4 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Old Lyrics [5 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Old Lyrics [6 of 6] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Saddest Day in the Whole World [zine] [1 of 2], undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    This tribute zine is dedicated to the memory of Molly Ann McMahon and contains multiple color photos and illustrations of the subject at various ages. Also contains a short writing passage.
  - The Saddest Day in the Whole World [Zine] [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Bikini Kill/Riot Grrrl Memorabilia [1 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Bikini Kill/Riot Grrrl Memorabilia [2 of 6], undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Bikini Kill/Riot Grrrl Memorabilia [3 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bikini Kill/Riot Grrrl Memorabilia [4 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bikini Kill/Riot Grrrl Memorabilia [5 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bikini Kill/Riot Grrrl Memorabilia [6 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Julie Ruin Correspondence and Album Art, 1997-1998 (Box Shared Fales 041, Folder 19)
  - Julie Ruin Press [1 of 3], undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Julie Ruin Press [2 of 3], undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Julie Ruin Press [3 of 3], undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Julie Ruin Memories [1 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Julie Ruin Memories [2 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Julie Ruin Memories [3 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Julie Ruin Memories [4 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Julie Ruin Memories [5 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Julie Ruin Memories [6 of 6], undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Julie Ruin Press Kit/One Sheets [1 of 2], undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Julie Ruin Press Kit/One Sheets [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Julie Ruin Photos [1 of 2], [1997] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Juie Ruin Photos [2 of 2], [1997] (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Le Tigre graphics [1 of 2], [2001] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Le Tigre graphics [2 of 2] [Kathleen Hanna's Original Folder], [2001] (Box 6, Folder 4)